Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ andrewknuppel (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Community Outreach
Public Speaking
Adobe Creative Suite

Languages

English (Native or Bilingual) Spanish (Limited Working)

Certifications

American Institute of Certified Planners
Certified Floodplain Manager

Honors-Awards

Raven Society
Intermediate Honors
Dean's List

Eagle Scout

Virginia Chapter of the American Planning Association Outstanding Student Award

Andrew Knuppel, AICP, CFM

Director of Community Planning at Asakura Robinson Austin, Texas, United States

Summary

Andrew Knuppel serves as Director of Community Planning in Asakura Robinson's Austin studio. He is excited about the power of great design, thoughtful policy, and high-touch community engagement to empower community action and facilitate conversations around today's pressing issues. Having spent time in the Midwest, the Southeast, the Mid-Atlantic, and now Texas, he enjoys learning about and celebrating the histories, defining qualities, and quirks of the places he works and lives in. His planning perspective is shaped by experiences working in local government, floodplain management, and hazard mitigation.

Prior to joining Asakura Robinson, Andrew led a team of planners with Texas A&M AgriLife Extension Service's Texas Community Watershed Partners in Houston, conducting resilience-focused educational workshops and technical assistance projects and supporting a network of disaster assessment and recovery professionals across the state of Texas. Before moving to Texas, Andrew worked in a variety of neighborhood planning and zoning administration roles with Albemarle County, Virginia.

Andrew is a proud graduate of the University of Virginia, holding an undergraduate and graduate degrees in urban and environmental planning. In his free time, Andrew enjoys exploring the local food scene, bike infrastructure, and historic markers.

Experience

Asakura Robinson Senior Planner November 2022 - Present (1 year) Austin, Texas, United States Texas Community Watershed Partners, Texas A&M AgriLife Extension

2 years 1 month

Planning Program Manager
December 2021 - October 2022 (11 months)

Houston, Texas, United States

Planning Team Lead / Program Coordinator II October 2020 - December 2021 (1 year 3 months)

Houston, Texas, United States

I lead the Texas Community Watershed Partners (TCWP) planning team in a variety of flood hazard mitigation and community planning activities, including applications of the CHARM (Community Health and Resource Management) platform.

Oversee CHARM Resiliency Workshops in Texas communities, including workshop organization, stakeholder outreach, and facilitation.

Supervise a technical assistance program and manage individual planning assistance projects, including zoning and subdivision ordinance writing, GIS analyses, and hazard mitigation project identification exercises.

Present information about TCWP programs and CHARM's applications for risk assessment and community engagement in partnership with state and federal partners.

Support program development and administration, including grant reporting and compliance.

Provide support to other programs and projects as needed.

Albemarle County
3 years 10 months
Senior Neighborhood Planner
July 2020 - October 2020 (4 months)

Charlottesville, Virginia, United States

Neighborhood Planner June 2018 - July 2020 (2 years 2 months) Charlottesville, Virginia Area

Supported long-range planning efforts including the Rio29 Small Area Plan (2018), Pantops Master Plan (2019), and Crozet Master Plan (2019-2020). Provided staff support to the Crozet and 5th & Avon Community Advisory Committees.

Maintained geospatial and demographic datasets and conduct analysis in support of planning efforts.

Managed performance reporting efforts including the Indicators of Progress portion of the Planning Commission's Annual Report.

Launched a public-facing Development Dashboard tool to improve access to information on active development projects.

Principal author of the 2019 Growth Management Report, which analyzed development trends and the ability of the County's land use policies to accommodate expected growth.

Zoning Planner

August 2017 - June 2018 (11 months)

Charlottesville, Virginia

Performed general zoning administration tasks, including development right and parking determinations and letters of zoning compliance.

Reviewed personal wireless service facility, building, and legislative permit applications for compliance with the County's Zoning Ordinance.

Assisted in long-range planning efforts and preliminary scoping of a form-based code zoning text amendment.

Initiated public-facing process improvements including redesigns of application forms and pre-application conferences.

Planning Intern

January 2017 - August 2017 (8 months)

Charlottesville, Virginia Area

Researched performance metrics and prepared the Planning Commission's 2016 Annual Report, which was recognized by the American Planning Association's Virginia Chapter at their 2018 conference.

Analyzed the County's theoretical residential development capacity for future land use, current zoning, and environmental constraints using Esri ArcGIS.

University of Virginia Marketing Assistant / Graphic Designer September 2016 - May 2017 (9 months)

Office of the Dean of Students

Designed and coordinated promotions, social media, and branding for the units within the University's Office of the Dean of Students. Updated & maintained wayfinding materials for the Newcomb Hall student center.

The University of Virginia School of Architecture Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

August 2016 - December 2016 (5 months)

ARCH 1020 (Lessons In Making)

Served as a Teaching Assistant for the foundation design course for undergraduates in the School of Architecture.

Attended lectures and a weekly teaching seminar, co-led section workshops, provided guidance to students, and graded projects.

CSX Transportation
Public Affairs - Strategic Infrastructure Intern
May 2015 - August 2015 (4 months)
Jacksonville, FL

Created a framework to assess the economic and social effects of intermodal freight rail infrastructure development on local and regional levels. Collaborated with internal and external stakeholders to identify case studies, relevant metrics, and topics; produced a final presentation and economic profiles for the areas and projects studied.

Reported to the Vice President of Strategic Infrastructure Initiatives.

Education

The University of Virginia School of Architecture

Master of Urban & Environmental Planning (2019 - 2020)

University of Virginia

Bachelor of Urban and Environmental Planning, Urban and Environmental Planning; Economics (Architecture Minor) · (2013 - 2017)